When you work
professionally as a software engineer,
this is not practicing a hobby.
You need to have numbers, right?
Not just fluffy words.
What was the actual landed impact
on the business?
Sometimes solving business problems
means building software.
That is good enough.
Good enough for today.
I just want things to be simple.
Simple is complicated enough,
especially at scale.
System design.
A skill that separates
good engineers from great ones.
So if you want to level up as software
engineer, this conversation is for you.
Joining me today is Bassem Dghaidi,
senior software engineer over at GitHub.
And especially a GitHub,
they operate at scale.
He shares how they design their software
and solve specific problems
in a way I didn't expect. So enjoy.
Beyond Coding.
From an outside service.
I feel like I've shared this many times
on the podcast, but I feel like the tech
community is quite unique.
People create software,
they create products,
and they put them out in the open
for free.
And GitHub is like the backbone
that enables a lot of these things.
I feel like I don't see no other industry,
and it's it's kind of typical
for me to say that
because I'm in this industry,
but I don't see any similar other industry
where this is possible.
Precisely.
And not only that, like the learning,
the teaching aspect that we have,
how openly we share what we learn,
and we have this status associated
with people
who actually teach in our industry,
which I don't often see elsewhere.
A lot of industries
and I worked in other industries,
like I've worked in container terminals,
for example, for a while we were building
the whole infrastructure and whatnot.
It's very rare to find information
about how a container terminal operates,
unless you've, like,
went to a specific program
that teaches that we're taking specialized
courses.
You're never going to get that information
anyway.
Like there are no blog posts
that describe how things work.
Yeah, you just gotta learn it either
from people who have been doing
or practicing this industry for a while,
or if
you go through a specialized program.
So I definitely relate to what you're
saying, and I think it's pretty unique,
which is awesome.
There are some topics that I have in mind,
and especially
that I think are going to be a bigger
focal point going towards the future.
Something like system design,
where there's a lot of theory out there
and then actually putting it in practice.
You can understand the theory,
but then putting it to practice
is still very challenging, especially in
what type of organization you are.
How far in the future
are you going to design?
I feel like it's challenging bridging
the gap between theory and practice
for that aspect 100%.
And I was thinking about this
topic earlier today, right?
I was just reading a post on ECS
that went viral
where a startup was talking
about the migration to Kubernetes
and that it almost,
cost them their startup, like, oh, well,
the startup could have almost failed
because of that particular migration,
and the owner was listing the reasons
why they went for the migrations,
and none of them were technical
like the reasons were.
The reasons were pushing for cloud native.
Okay, their engineers wanted
the Kubernetes experience and,
they thought that they can deploy
faster, bigger scale, better.
But what they ended up with
is just a fatter AWS bill.
And then the much more competition
feature shipment crawled to a halt.
They had to dedicate
certain engineers for this.
And I think this stems from the fact
that a lot of people
want the status associated
with fancy architectures,
and they want the experience
of working with fancy architectures
and not necessarily solving problems
with fancy architectures, or growing
organically a certain architecture
to solve a particular problem.
And the problem with system design
is, again,
a lot of people want the fancy stuff,
but they
the boundaries for when you need to scale
are very blurry.
There are no concrete empirical numbers
that tell you,
like when you hit this particular scale,
you need to do this.
And when you hit this particular number,
you need to do that.
So people assume that as soon as they hit
on their service or API or whatever,
like a thousand requests per second,
that's a lot.
So now they need to build
for the next evolution of the system.
And often that's not really the case.
At GitHub, for example,
I've built services that handle millions
of requests per second
that are just simply running on a 5
or 6 containers and a very tiny Kubernetes
cluster somewhere.
That's not what I would expect at all.
So there's a lot there's a lot
you can do with very little,
and you can even run entire services
on very basic VMs
and scale some stuff around it.
And the way we approach problems of scale,
we never design or engineer.
So when I design certain things,
I recently did a lot of that.
We were rewriting some parts of actions,
GitHub actions.
That's what I work on.
So we're going to talk more
about that and engineering blog posts
and what this is like, in my opinion,
a case study for decades to come,
because this doesn't often happen.
That's awesome.
Yeah.
So, when we were designing this,
we were designing for scale,
but we know already
we have established scale.
So we know that we've hit the limit of
what the previous architecture could do.
And now is the point
where we need to squeeze more
out of a different tech
stack to get to that next level.
And we know that we're going
to get to that next level because we
we see the demand,
we see how it's growing.
We see the curve.
We see how where it's going to
be in five years from.
Right.
So we solved for that.
We didn't prematurely scale.
We just went all the way till the end
with the existing architecture.
Okay.
And that's when we made the decision
to rewrite some components and redesign
certain aspects of it
and make tradeoffs based on data
we had and based on projections
that we were going to attain or get.
Is this then your advice as well?
So to stick with what you have,
start with initial design that is simple
and then stick with it
until you actually reach certain limits.
And you can kind of based on your usage
forecast what the next iteration would be.
If I was a startup founder
or a CTO of a startup, right.
I would never go and start
building for 100 x scale, even if I'm a
like a firm believer in my idea and know
that it's going to reach the masses
and it's going to be global,
I would never design for that.
I would design for getting 100 users
and maybe even 1000, right.
And I would just run everything
on a single VM, to be honest.
Maybe to
make it a bit more available.
I would not go and build massive database
clusters.
Yeah, just start with one, maybe two
nodes.
Stops replication. That's it.
And this will like really,
really far, to be honest.
Once I attain or I'm get,
I'm like close to 80% of these limits
my resources can do.
And by the way,
vertical scaling can take you a long way.
Like you have no idea.
We have
large scale nodes
that have hundreds of CPUs on them.
So you don't really need to go
and start sharding
and doing all sorts of fancy stuff.
When vertical scaling consists at you
and you
right now with cloud native solutions,
you can go pretty far.
Like you can get a one
VM with 120 CPU cores, right?
You can get terabytes of memory.
Yeah, and that can do a lot for you.
You don't need to start doing
horizontal scaling
before you get
you really start hitting these limits.
Interesting.
See, I, I feel like I'm
not great at system design.
It's just not something
that I specifically put my thoughts to,
not something
I prepared like from an interview style.
And then I actually did a system
design interview and my architecture was
it was very simple,
and I wanted it to be simple
because I don't like complexity
when we don't need it.
And it was also for the use case.
I was like,
this is this is the simple aspect.
And then the question was, okay,
but what if we had x amount of scale
and then we need indeed
we need high availability
and we need sharding
and we need consistency.
And then I was like but the like
the argument that I had is in this case,
it actually doesn't matter for me,
the part of the benefit that we have
a lot of information out there
people can self-advocate
is not also turning into this pitfall
where complex system design is almost,
I think in most industries
where we don't actually have high
availability across
the globe is not needed.
Yeah, yeah, people see that
and they look up to big organizations
like GitHub where they say, okay,
this is what GitHub has.
So we're going to do the same.
We're going to build for the future 100%.
And this is in my opinion, again,
going back to the original thought
that people's Chase status.
So and this was honestly
also very badly
perpetuated by big tech companies.
Right.
And a lot of
people followed, like in an interview for,
for if you're interviewing for a place
like GitHub, for example,
it's understandable
that they would want you or that
they want to explore problems of scale
with you just because
from day one, you're going to be exposed
to these problems.
So what we are, what we are looking for
is typically is people who have
that experience, who are going to come in
and actually use it on day one.
Yeah, not that
we might use it in a few years time.
We just hire for what we need today
because let's say you're shipping,
you're shipping features to a service,
and a lot of our services
have hundreds of millions of requests
and short periods of time.
So you cannot really do a lot of the,
you need to think about a lot of things,
right?
You need to think about caching
from the bit from day zero.
You need to think about your queries.
From there, you need to think about
your data access patterns.
You need to think about non-relational
databases and non-relational solutions
for whatever you're building.
You need to think about how you're going
to gradually deploy this.
You need to think about feature flags,
how they're going to play in this game.
You're going to think about authorization,
authentication,
all of the security problems
that might happen when you have this
security problem at at some other place
like GitHub, it's going to be on the news.
Yeah.
Or less. Right.
So you cannot make these mistakes.
It's very tricky.
So we look for experience in these domains
so that people
they still have this room tonight, but
they need to deliver from very early on.
Right.
For smaller companies,
they interview for the same,
but they don't need it.
And that's where the problems
that's where the problem stands.
If I was in a startup and I'm into I'm
doing system design, I would interview,
I would want to hear from a person
who has exactly what we need for today.
If we got to 100 million tomorrow.
Yeah.
We start hiring for tomorrow
when we get to it.
To be honest.
And with the churn rate in our industry
being 2 or 3 years,
like people don't stay in the same job
for more than that.
Why would you, you know, hire
for the next ten years?
The person. Yeah.
I feel like people really underestimate,
like,
how much they should or overestimate how
much they should design for the future.
Like a I'm in a consultancy right now.
I go from assignment to assignment
and some assignments that I've been in,
I'm like,
the system is way too complex
for what we had.
We used to have 30 engineers.
Now we have eight, and the system we
architected was maintained by 30 people.
And now we have a problem because we only
have eight because budget is running out.
We're behind on KPIs because like the we
we worked on a big rocket ship,
but we actually needed a car.
We needed to drive
and actually make meters.
And, and I talk about this stuff
in my system
design course because in consulting
and when you sell a solution to a company.
The company wants to pay for that solution
once. Yeah.
They don't understand
that software is evolved.
It's not built.
Right.
And the the term here is evolving it.
So software needs to continuously
be evolved and it needs to continuously
fight entropy in the sense
that you continuous need to maintain it.
That is a fixed or running cost
for maintenance of software
that you don't necessarily
find in other industries.
When you buy a car,
there is a cost for maintaining it, but
it's not very regular
or as regular as software.
Right.
And our industry,
the maintenance cost is pretty high.
So companies
want to pay once for a solution
and they want it to scale to the next
ten x 100 x.
And that's not very realistic
in our industry at all.
We need to build literally
for the next order of
of magnitude.
So if we are ideal
today, just build for ten x or 100 x.
Yeah.
If we add a ten x or a hundred x,
we build for the other author, right.
1000, 1 million, so on and so forth.
What is then your perspective
on building systems that can evolve?
Because some people you can say, okay,
this is the system design that we have,
and we're going to continue on this
until we reach a certain level of scale,
and then we're going to revamp
and say this would be the next iteration.
But some people also say, okay,
we have a system now, and this is able to
whatever scale we need.
And then they put in the extra effort
to make sure that that is there
from the beginning in our industry,
very few technologies
last for like a decade plus,
and the rest is changing.
Often.
And that's why I personally don't invest,
or I wouldn't design a solution
that would last like ten, 20, 30 years,
unlike what we did in the 80s or 90s.
That's what
that's how that was the design mentality.
But things were way
less complicated than they are today,
and the scale was different.
So I would always come with the mindset
that I'm just going to design
for the next order of magnitude,
and then I'm going to evolve it
from there.
And that's going to require
another round of investment.
There's going to be continual investments
in this and that business
people are not going to love this
because that makes accounting much harder.
That makes strategic finance much harder
because they cannot predict
or anticipate
the costs that might come in the future.
They cannot extrapolate from today.
You know,
they don't like this fuzziness software.
It's all risk. Yes.
So and also like they cannot calculate
like their bottom line
or projections for the future,
which are things that are very realistic,
like publicly, publicly traded companies
want to be able to do these projections,
and they want to be able to say that, hey,
we're not going to be spending more here
than on evolving our software,
but we're going to make much more revenue
and increase our bottom line and margin.
That's what businesses look for.
So it's understandable.
But from a software perspective,
there needs to be regular investments.
And I think the only approachable way,
which is something we do at
GitHub, is to continuously revisit
these investments on a quarterly
by quarterly, half a year or a year basis.
Right.
We can make projections
for the next three, four, five years,
but the confidence in these projections
is less and less and less.
Yeah, more time goes.
And I think a lot more companies
need to start doing the same.
When you say we will then design
for the next level,
the order of magnitude for the next level,
how far in the horizon do you look at what
the GitHub actions example that you had?
You said, okay, five years,
but is that like an arbitrary thing
or how depends on the curve, right.
It depends on the GitHub like GitHub
actions has been growing massively over
since we, we we brought it up,
at the beginning, and we're introducing
more and more features
that are increasing the adoption.
So the curve we can see how it looks like.
Yeah. But it might change at any point
in time. Right.
It can be disrupted close to zero
or it can continue growing exponentially.
So often the hockey stick
that a lot of tech startups
talk about, like exponential growth,
it can appear and you can start seeing it.
And when you start seeing it,
you know, see how the solution
like actions, companies that migrate to it
are not going to flip flop. No.
And very short periods of time be there
so you can have some confidence that,
okay, this trend is going to last
for a year or two or 3 or 4, right?
Nothing lasts forever, obviously.
But you can start thinking
in that direction.
And then based on that,
you can make investment decisions.
Gotcha.
I've had many discussions also in the past
when we were talking about our software
architecture
in something that can be very specific
and also purposeful, built versus
setting it up in a generic way.
But then it should be towards the future,
because we have ambitions
and hopes that we have
X amount of solutions that are similar.
So we make a generic right now,
what is your perspective on
making something specific versus
generic in the first place?
I like solving specific problems.
I don't like solving generic problems
because how can you make tradeoffs then?
Right.
Well, in software
there's always trade offs.
So how do you choose these trade offs?
You can build something
super generic. Sure.
That basically is why building a framework
that can be a toolbox
and give you all sorts of solutions
to all sorts
of hypothetical problems
that you might or might not have.
That's not the Northstar
I follow when I design software at GitHub.
With my team, we
are very
specific about not overengineering things,
and we solve for the problems
we have today.
So for example, we never introduce caching
until we really need it,
and we never over optimize
until we start seeing problems.
Sometimes, sometimes we we know
that we're going to hit this problem
a few months
and we're not going to get the investment.
So we solve it right now
because it makes sense.
But we don't over engineer solutions.
We don't start jumping into things.
For example, we don't necessarily jump
to NoSQL at the beginning.
We just start regular
relational databases.
You know, we build regular tables
if we need if we need actually relational,
content.
Sometimes relational databases
can always get so far.
So we start needing to three
think our solutions here.
And we need to start going towards
non-relational.
Even if we need
the relational consistency,
or the consistency of relational
databases, we need to start thinking about
how can we move that to the application
layer
and start using other solutions
that persist data that can help us scale?
Yeah, there are some efforts, for example,
where we start using cosmos or
cosmos DB and things like that,
but we
never start exploring these
until we hit really massive problems
with our database clusters
like our primaries cannot keep up.
The IO is pretty high.
Right? Operations are substantially big.
We cannot scale these anymore.
Sharding is not an option.
Application
layer sharding is not an option as well.
When it becomes not an option,
sometimes it is.
So we started thinking about
how can we design this
and how can we migrate the data and
migrations as much as they are painful,
they are part of the job.
Yeah, interesting.
And we do go through them.
I'm wondering
when we talk about system design
and then specifically
practical experience,
what your perspective is on
someone to really get
a better understanding of the theory,
but also be able to put it in practice.
You like you already mentioned that,
for example, like GitHub,
you need to have a certain
level of experience under your belt
and then you can work at GitHub
where we have orders of magnitude
with regards to scale.
This is a vicious cycle, right?
So do you. How do you
how do you build experience
that is required
by this type of companies.
But there's no other type of company
that's going to give you that experience.
Unfortunately there's that's that's
the reason why there is a proliferation
of a lot of system
design courses and things online.
And quite honestly,
passing that into passing the interview
threshold for companies like GitHub.
That is
achievable by learning
theoretically these concepts, okay,
and not necessarily
having hands on experience with them.
The bar feels high,
but right now it's been sort of
exploited to the point
where a lot of the tricks
and tips and whatnot are already available
very much online.
Like, I know, interview you guys, for
example, they have this YouTube channel.
They have pretty much covered
a lot of the topics that you might get
asked in a system design interview.
Okay.
And they go deep
like they explain what Kafka
is, what event streaming, as they explain.
Right, is the internals, how it works,
when do you use it?
When not to use it?
They explain the differences between
relational and relational databases.
They explain caching, how to implement
caching in specific scenarios,
and they give practical, hands on problems
where you can actually learn
how to effectively utilize
all of these different components
to come up
with a relatively scalable solution.
And they give you tips
also on how to approach
the discussion of scale
within a system design interview.
And I think
they do a pretty good job at it.
And I think that's enough,
because a lot of people who go to big
Tech will go to Google, and they don't
necessarily have that hands on experience
beforehand, even though the interview
is looking for that hands on experience.
But, you know, with these,
because we hack the people.
Hack the game. Yeah.
So the signal is given to the interviewer.
And then people when they have these,
this foundation, they can actually
do a relatively
okay job on, when they join
and they've got obviously
not going to be a right.
So you're never going to join a team
and start
building greenfield stuff from day zero.
It rarely happens where you're going to
join teams that are already established.
So there's going to be people
with experience more senior
than you are going to give you guidance
and review your solutions, your designs,
so on and so forth.
And that's why people make it right.
But if you are interviewed for experience
and you join a greenfield project,
you know, you going to own your mistakes.
And people do make mistakes often.
Yeah.
When it comes to these solutions,
not everything big tech
ships is a great feature or operates
well in the world.
And often we discover that, oh, this was a
mistake and it was actually very costly.
And some companies fail
because of this researcher.
Right?
Any failures or mistakes
that are top of mind for you
that you can share
for other people to learn?
Tricky.
No, I want to keep my job so
that's fair.
That's fair for me.
Looking at what we do nowadays,
I feel with AI tools and we're
more productive in actually writing code.
And I feel like when you amplify
the amount of code that you write,
you might also write yourself
into a bottleneck, basically.
So I feel like software architecture and
specifically system design from the start,
having a better understanding,
especially I feel like like I do now,
I need to grow there and I feel like it's
going to be a more important skill
to indeed figure out what are we designing
for, what makes sense?
What would be the next order of magnitude
after, and actually
make sure to convince people
and have a certain level of buy in.
We're always working in teams.
Also, from a business standpoint,
how would I, for example, say
we're going to design for this
until we reach scale
and then we're going to need to revamp,
and this is what that's going to entail
for people that don't understand
how to build software,
understand the business constraints.
So you're never going to be able
to convince the business folks
about of something.
Technically,
they're just it's too abstract.
Even if it feels too intuitive
for us, for them, it's magic.
Yeah.
And even if they try to understand
how things work, they're never going
to comprehend the magnitude of problems.
And they're never going to
have this intuition about how software is
and how not hard,
you know, how how involved it is.
So it's our job
to get closer to their side.
Some people say, no,
we want the business to understand.
They're not gonna.
It's trickier.
It's easier for you to acquire, assimilate
some of the not everything,
some of the business constraints
and discuss them from that perspective.
And that's why a lot of engineers
who grow are very good at understanding
the business constraints
and then discussing the technical
solutions within those constraints.
So for example, I used to work in the
container terminal industry for a while.
We built a huge container terminal.
We furnished everything
from the fiber optics
layer
all the way to the three tier data center.
With all of the enterprise applications
running and running on it,
and the operating system
for the container,
and it's one of the most
massive operations you can ever imagine.
One of the most hazardous as well.
So the folks, they're there
as far away from tech as possible.
You're not never going
to find the terminal operator
who's going to understand what it means
that your database is running hot
and you cannot support their case.
All they care about is, I have a ship
here, was docked.
There's like, 10,000 containers on it.
I need to empty them into my yard.
I have a very fixed window of time,
and if I don't do it
in that window of time,
this is going to cost me money.
We were operating at 12% capacity.
That terminal was generating
about $50,000 per hour.
So 12%.
So you can imagine if we get delayed
every minute of delay is actually money
that's disappearing.
So this is how you need to discuss
problems and investments and solutions.
You need to understand what the impact
is, what the impact is on the operators.
And sometimes it's life threatening
impact, right.
If your software fails when a STS
when the crane is offloading a container,
this can be a very life
threatening situation.
You cannot really have your software
malfunction at this point.
So sloppiness of the software
sub millisecond latencies,
all of these things matter, right?
So you need to approach the discussions
with the stakeholders. Yes.
By understanding them first.
So what I've done, for
example, in the industry is
I've literally sat on a truck
and went there
and I sat with every single individual
who works in that terminal
to really understand
what they go through on a daily basis.
So a truck driver who's driving a truck
for six, seven, eight hours
and it was in Saudi Arabia in scorching
heat, it's not going to understand
like the button that they clicked
is just it's so
slow. Doesn't matter.
Doesn't he doesn't care.
He just wants it to just work.
So you got to understand
all of these perspectives.
And then when you do
you can start approaching
discussions from that vantage point.
And this applies to banks.
This applies
to hospitals to any other industry.
So understand the industry understand
the business constraints.
And then any technical solution
you want to discuss an investment,
you can approach it
from that vantage point.
Then you're going to have much
more success in these conversations.
Yeah. Interesting.
I feel like the
the opposite then also holds true.
So if you do understand the business
context and you don't have a case for
why you need to work on that,
why you need to scale,
well, you need to fix some of the issues,
then there might not be an actual case.
And right now is not the right time to do
so. Okay.
I do feel like it's it is a lot of
prep work that you have to do.
It's way easier
to talk about the technical things right?
Because that's what you see.
That's what you perceive latency,
numbers, storage, scalability.
That's what you look at.
And then reframing it and saying, okay,
what is the impact for the business?
What is the cost per feature?
And what if we have, slower delivery rate
compared to a faster in a new future?
Yeah.
Talking that language is very different
from what you're used to.
Absolutely.
And the trickiest part, in my opinion, is
when the stakeholders
are not transparent about the numbers.
So they're never going to tell you like,
oh, we're making this $10 million
investment today
in this piece of software.
Because the investor,
one of the biggest investors
we have,
is willing to put that money in right now.
But nobody has the guts to go
tell him that.
No, we need another 10,000,000
in 10 years.
Yeah, right.
And nobody's
going to come in and tell you that.
But you need to also think about it.
Try to extract that information,
try to understand
who was funding this,
what is funding this, what is critical?
What is the business in jeopardy?
Is it right now under a lot of scrutiny?
Is the bottom line not working?
Is the margin of profit not that high?
But what is driving
this particular investment right now?
Is it more strategic?
So I worked in building banks,
for example, in the in the Gulf
I worked as a consultant as well.
Right. So,
there were banks
that wanted to make a one shot
investment into what they thought
that was their future.
And they had a lump
sum of money that they wanted
to put down once and build software
that will last them for ten years.
Yeah.
They're not going to they
nobody has the guts to come in
and tell somebody, an executive
who has no time whatsoever that, hey,
well this investment is good.
I see maybe like two, three, four years,
but you need to put in also
another million every year to maintain it
and maybe even another 10,000,000 in 5,
six years, because you need to keep up
with the new trends.
Nobody has the guts to come in
and say that at the beginning,
because then the decision maker might say,
oh, well,
this is not worth it for me anymore.
Yeah, we might just scratch it
completely. Precisely.
What I've also seen
is that some organizations operate
with a number of engineers.
And then from an outside standpoint,
I have no clue
what those engineers are doing.
Like,
if I look at a specific e-commerce website
that might have 2000 engineers
work, kind of a similar
one with a similar level of skill,
might have a few hundred.
And then I feel like
the few hundred engineers,
they need to have a bigger landscape
of ownership, understanding
what they do in the context of the day
to day on a business
side is easier for them
than being part of a group of 2000
engineers.
That kind of does the same in scale,
if you like.
If you're a cog, it's very hard to argue
what kind of optimizing your little cog
is going to do for the greater good.
One thing I
one thing a lot of
people hate,
but I think is very functional.
And a lot of the companies
that operate based on the San Francisco
Silicon Valley model is the ruthlessness
in terms of optimizing how engineers work,
and layoffs.
So in Europe, layoffs are not
it's very famous for,
a very well received thing,
and I don't think they are very well
received in the US as well.
But they are.
And if they are an effective mechanism,
even though it's dehumanizing,
but it is an effective mechanism
to recalibrate how people
or where people put their attention
and what they are focusing on.
So in a lot of situations,
when layoffs happen,
there's a huge product, features
that are cut entirely, like,
we don't need this anymore. Yeah.
And it's it's more expensive
to repurpose the skills
of those same engineers in other areas.
So let's just cut it off immediately.
Hiring new engineers that are more
experienced in that particular domain.
Get them to focus on this right away.
So this rapid,
flexibility and moving
and rotating resources or people basically
allows these companies
to be much more nimble, and effectively
or more effectively allocate engineers
to particular problems that matters today.
The second thing I also think is a good
that separates
a lot of the big tech companies from other
companies is your work or your reward
bonuses, growth, whatever is associated
with your business impact,
not your software engineering impact.
So you can come in and say,
oh, I built the most the biggest
Kubernetes cluster,
you know, known to the planet.
It's beautiful. It's amazing.
You're not going to get any of that
or any recognition for it
unless you justify why that was important.
What was the actual
landed impact on the business?
So what did it contribute to
in terms of our revenue?
Did it help us grow?
That didn't help us attract
more customers?
Did it solve a very hard problem for us
that it affect developer experience?
Are people more and you need to have
numbers, not just fluffy words.
So I think that's also
another very effective
way to reallocate attention software
engineers.
And it's very easy for us also software
to drift into the comfort zones.
So I'm building something
I'm comfortable in it.
Yeah.
And nobody's questioning me on it.
Nobody understands what I'm doing.
I just keep doing the same thing
every day.
Yeah, I feel like I've also shared this
previously on the podcast.
Some engineers that I've met,
they love the technical side of things.
And when you let them go wild, when
there's no business context or direction,
they will build you a rocket ship
and they will really enjoy doing it.
There is a craft,
the craftsmanship aspect of software
engineering is still there.
You know, there is an esthetic to it.
There is like, it's fun, it's enjoyable.
But I always in my even my social media
starts
like I always strive to communicate that
when you work professionally as software
engineer, this is not practicing a hobby.
And I think a lot of this craftsmanship,
thinking comes from the fact
that a lot of people
went into software engineer
because programing was a hobby
for them, myself included.
I started writing code when and stuff.
I thought that this is amazing
if I can make it my job perfect.
But the job is very different
than practicing code
for the sake of writing code
and the esthetics and the fun of it.
Sometimes you are lucky to be able
to bring that into your work,
but most often you're not really solving
for the esthetic.
You're solving a business problem,
and you need to keep that in mind
always and often.
It's not about the beauty of your skin.
And if you can build a beautiful solution
and solve the business problem
effectively, fantastic.
That's the cherry on top. Win-Win.
But the priorities
for the business problem
and sometimes solving business problems
means building software.
That is good
enough, good enough for today,
right?
Doesn't
have to be good enough for tomorrow.
Maybe it's horrible for tomorrow,
but it just keeps on functioning.
Yeah, and this investment we did in
the good enough
is going to give us a certain runway.
And we should be okay with that.
I think we should be okay with that.
That's what I've seen where it's
challenging for people, where they say,
okay, I'm a little bit of a perfectionist.
I value quality
in what I do on a day to day.
My job is basically part of who I am,
and if I don't deliver the highest quality
that I can in this aspect,
like I'm doing myself with this justice.
And it's very like if I lay it out
like that, it might sound selfish,
but I still have no clue
that what they're saying is selfish.
They genuinely think it's best
for the organization.
It's just some misinformation
and misunderstanding because there's
a dogmatic aspect of software engineering,
and it was perpetuated in the previous era
until 2000, 2000 and I
when I ventured in working professionals,
software engineer, 2007 eight nine,
there was a lot of dogma,
like there's a lot of
this is how you do things
and this is how you should do things.
And if you do things
any other way, you're wrong. Yeah.
And part of that is elegance of code code,
cleanliness code quality.
You're all raised on this, these
these concepts. Right.
And they're important.
And everybody always complained
about bad code and horrible code
because it was difficult to maintain.
Nobody enjoys that.
You're going to make it very difficult
for the future engineers
to solve these problems.
But sometimes,
you know, you don't have future engineers
to solve these problems.
Sometimes nobody's going to touch
this code for decades to come.
It's okay if it's just it just works.
And then we ended up on the complete
other end of the spectrum
where we tried to clean up
everything that we started adopting.
All sorts of design,
overcomplicated abstractions that are
are just horrible to me.
How horrible to reason about
it takes you decades to become proficient
in just reading that type of code.
And then when you write it,
it gets even more
complicated and it's very difficult
to maintain, in big Tech.
And I always tell my colleagues
in the juniors that report to me,
simple is complicated enough,
especially at scale.
Yeah.
So just write it in the dumbest,
most simple way possible.
This is why I also love code, for example.
That's allowed.
You do write. Yes.
It's amazing. It's dumb.
You don't have to
think too much. It's
just all in your face.
Whenever you want to understand
how something is built,
you just trace it
around. It's there, it's there.
Fantastic. I love that.
And in the situations
where we're building at scale,
I don't want to reason about abstractions.
I don't want to think about edge cases.
I don't want to think about complicated
memory allocations
and complicated memory structures.
You know, I just want things to be simple.
Memory leaks happen often,
and they are very catastrophic at scale.
I don't want to think about these things.
I don't want to think about
how my garbage collector is going to,
you know, shut down the whole world
and start causing multi second latency
on my API requests, which at scale again
become a gigantic problem for me.
I just want things to be
simple, easy to reason about.
And that's it.
Yeah. And interesting.
I also feel like we've
we are now in a trend where
there is this conversation
happening with people that are,
first of all, vibe coding, loving it,
being effective in what they do,
solving a problem through software
and they don't care how it looks.
And then you have the older part,
let's say existing software engineers
that look at this and say
both from a craft perspective
and from an execution perspective,
how does this work? Right.
This is kind of really coming into
my territory, I feel uncomfortable.
Do I jump on this?
Do I actually like it,
or is this going to take away what I love
dearly, what I used to do day to day?
I think in essence, things are evolving.
For me, that's a fact.
The question is, where is it going?
And I'm curious
to see your perspective on a funny,
it happens in every community,
to be honest.
So I'm starting my,
a motorcycle riding classes.
Okay, okay.
And in motorcycle riding, a lot of the
more advanced motorcyclist motorcyclists,
they love manual, the clutch, they love,
you know, changing gears.
They love the
the controlling the, the motorcycle
in every single aspect, especially when
they attain that level of proficiency.
So a lot of them are now resisting
a lot of the motorcycle companies
introducing clutches or clutches
that just operate automatically.
They hate that.
I don't want this like I want to control
every single aspect of my bike.
Right.
And I feel
this is pretty much the same thing
that what's happening in software,
a lot of the folks who have attained
a high level of proficiency
and they enjoy the craftsmanship
aspect of software development,
they love the coding part.
They love
reasoning about code structure, syntax.
They get a kick out of coming up
with a smarter solution, where they
utilize a
syntactical, feature
and a programing language to do something
that was not maybe designed for
or do something smart with it.
So if you take that away from them,
you're basically introducing, you know, it
clutches to software development
and they're not going to react positively
to it, even though the clutches help
like when, for example, in
when you're stopping at a
at the light signal,
you don't have to worry about stalling
and you don't have to worry
about these things.
It just makes your life much easier, fun
to ride the the sight for the motorcycle.
It's just easier to control it.
More accessible. Yeah. More accessible.
So like, lighting
is pretty much the same thing.
I hate the term white coding
because right now at GitHub, for example,
I literally and this is part
of my presentation at universe,
90% of my code is written by agents.
So I use the VS code
agent mode all the time.
Yeah.
And I've been shipping features
to production with it all the time.
But that's not something
you should just write and code, right?
There's a lot of other stuff.
Yeah, that come to it.
And I now shift
my focus towards the operational problems.
I shift my focus towards
making sure that we never go down.
making sure that I don't
introduce bugs that are unnecessary
and cause people to have pain,
because GitHub has become part
of the infrastructure of the internet now.
So any problem that I cause has
great ripple effects.
So that's where I put my focus on
right now.
Coding.
Fine.
Let the agent write it and I will
instruct it to write it in a certain way.
And if there's a syntactical
approach that I prefer better,
I still push it to to do that.
And if something looks funky to me, and
I also prompted to change the direction.
Right.
But at the same time,
one of the problems I was solving was
recently was a caching problem, right?
And I had different ways
to implement the cache key,
and each way
forced a certain data access pattern
because of how the key is structured.
And it had a different impact on Redis
based on how the keys structured.
So what I've done with this code
agent is I prompted it
to write different benchmarks. Yeah.
And I saw that, hey,
this pattern,
this pattern, in this pattern,
go write three distinct benchmarks,
run them, give me the results,
analyze them, and give me the output.
That's worked.
That could have been done
in like two three days.
Maybe that was done in 20 minutes.
Why not?
Fantastic. It's amazing. Yeah.
So you've been programing,
you said hands on coding when you were 12.
Have you always had this mindset
to kind of let go of more of the craft
things and look at what it is
from an execution standpoint?
Because I hear you from now
and it feels like you're very much
on board and making things more effective,
understanding the business context.
It's not just the craft,
because, no, I was never like that.
So when I was younger,
I was all about the craft.
And in I my early mentors,
I fought with them a lot times.
Right.
And I was lucky to have mentors. Right?
I was lucky,
to have great mentors
at the beginning of my career,
but they never were able to explain to me
why their perspective
of the business matters.
For me, business was too abstract, like,
I don't understand the numbers.
I didn't understand accounting.
I was not accountable for the business
outcomes.
I was just asked to solve a problem
and I thought I had
infinite business resources.
But when I realized that my mentors
sometimes,
took an extra mortgage on their house
just to pay the payroll
for their employees, oh, well,
that makes a different problem, right?
That gives perspective to the solutions
that you're going to come up with.
These are real people.
Company owners are not just all
millionaires and all, you know,
people who are not investing.
Some people are investing their own money
in, but building businesses, right?
So that matters.
So when you understand this and when you
become your business owner yourself,
you start thinking
about these things more.
And now I approach these problems
from that vantage point as well.
That doesn't mean that, again,
people might
I always get this argument
when I post about this stuff online.
People think, oh,
you write dirty code. No, I don't,
but there's a certain level
of the 20% that is required to reach
that highest level of esthetics.
Yeah, it's not worth it. No.
So I drop that. Gotcha.
As a final thought,
there's many people listening that learn
about software engineering and software
design in the first place
that either
are early in career, mid-career,
or are really just looking to level up
within their career.
What is your advice for people that really
want to become great software engineers?
What's
they need to do to increase your breath?
There's a lot of focus on that.
That's, early on in your career,
which is important.
And there's an advice that perpetuates
which says, focus,
true focus.
But at the same time, don't dismiss
everything else that's happening.
Increase your breadth.
Personally, I optimized
one thing that really got me far,
which is having the ability to learn
effectively in very short periods of time.
And that's why
whenever I tackle a problem,
I don't have a problem
digging very deep into anything new.
I encounter, from quantum mechanics
all the way
to any technical problem
that I face on a day to day basis.
I'm a,
you know, I mean, if I say drop out,
I never finished
my computer science education,
but that did not deter me from picking up
that education myself and really digging
deep into all sorts of theoretical topics,
but also practical areas and topics.
And I'm a perpetual learner.
So in my opinion,
the next phase where we're heading
is going to require people
to be able to learn really fast,
get out of their comfort
zone, really fast, dig deep really fast,
and attain high levels
of functional proficiency in any new area.
And then attaining mastery
is not always required in everything.
So just pick a few topics where you attain
mastery in, but also increase your bets.
Gotcha.
I think this is going to be very important
for the next phase.
I love the how do you get comfortable
with even saying,
I've gotten really good at picking up
new things and learning from quantum
mechanics to anything
technical, job related, whatever.
I have a lot of interests
and I see how fast
I can get to a working proficiency
with these interests.
I play music,
I'm learning to ride a motorcycle.
Right. So,
I never let's
if I'm curious about something,
I go and pursue it or I explore it,
and I never let
how complicated learning it
is deter me from pursuing it.
And I've become very comfortable
with being uncomfortable
learning something new.
And actually,
that gives me a joy and kick to the point
where it became sort of an addiction.
But, you know,
I keep it under control sometimes.
But I do enjoy the process of
and exploring something entirely different
and new, and in my opinion,
that has given me so much breadth
and the ability
to talk about all sorts of things.
But what I love the most about
it is how I can cross
different ideas together
from different disciplines
and have a much more diversified
view of the world,
and that gives me the ability to be able
to empathize also with all sorts of people
and different people, right,
and understand their vantage point.
So when someone's arguing with me,
I take a pause
and I try to reason
about where they're coming from,
what's their interest,
how they got to that idea.
But I draw from my own experiences
also in learning about all sorts of stuff,
including business and finance
and investments and all sorts
of all of these things. Right.
So I think that's richness.
And yeah, I would
definitely love for people
to be able to have that. Me too.
I think curiosity is a beautiful thing
when people say, I really don't have a
drive to learn something or to explore
something, I think it's a shame,
and I honestly don't know how to solve
that for people
to make sure they have that kind of love
for something or curiosity for something,
because I feel like that fuels drive
and that makes you move.
Absolutely. I don't know how to
I don't know if we really should
make people do anything.
I would love for people to have it. Yeah.
If they don't, you can.
There's a pretty,
you know, interesting life.
Still, some people have other commitments
as well.
Families, kids, less time, complicated
relationships in life happens.
It's understandable.
And that doesn't mean that I'm also 100%
always on the,
you know, on the burner,
learning every single minute of the day.
No, I have my life as well.
I have the complications of my life too.
So balance is important.
But I feel also curiosity is something
that you need to develop.
It's like a it's like a muscle.
You need to grow as well.
And approaching the world
from a curious vantage
point is way more interesting
and more effective
than being dogmatic or stubborn
or hardheaded about certain things.
You can have strong opinions,
but not before you actually did
your homework.
Yeah, absolutely.
Thanks so much for coming on and sharing.
This was a blast. Absolutely. My pleasure.
Going for hours. Me too.
We're going to rounded off here
if you're still with us.
Leave a comment in the comment section.
Let us know what you thought of this
episode and we'll see you on the next one.
Beyond Coding